Guide to the Henry Lewis Stimson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
In September, 1931, when Stimson was still deeply concerned over the world financial crisis, cables from the Far East indicated that Japan had invaded Manchuria in flagrant violation of the Kellogg Pact, the Nine Power Treaty, and the Covenant of the League of Nations. For three months Stimson continued to communicate with Kijuro Shidehara, Japan's foreign secretary. He hoped that the Japanese government could control the leaders of its armed forces, but Japanese aggression continued. By January 3, 1932, all of Manchuria was in Japanese hands. In reaction, Stimson decided to use moral sanctions. In a note to both China and Japan on January 7 he invoked the nonrecognition doctrine which was designed to reinforce the Kellogg Pact. If the fruits of aggression were recognized, Stimson believed, war would again be sanctioned as a legitimate instrument of national policy.
But this message did not deter the Japanese, who proceeded to attack Shanghai. Stimson, voicing United States policy, insisted on the maintenance of China's independence and territorial integrity. The Japanese refused to concur in the definition of China as an "organized people" and continued their advance. Stimson saw a sharp difference between the views of the East and West on these matters and predicted that if the friction between them continued it would be almost impossible to prevent an armed clash.
In the spring of 1932 Stimson attended the disarmament conference held in Geneva. In the summer he campaigned for the re-election of Hoover. After Hoover's defeat Stimson met with President--elect Roosevelt and Cordell Hull to discuss problems in foreign affairs, meanwhile preparing the way for conversations which he hoped to arrange between Roosevelt and the bitter Herbert Hoover, a plan which was never consummated.
In the interval between 1933 and 1940 Stimson divided his time between Washington and New York. Almost every summer he vacationed in Scotland. In 1936 he published a book about Japanese aggression titled The Far Eastern Crisis. In 1937 he was elected to serve a two-year term as president of the New York City Bar Association. He supported Roosevelt's basic views of foreign policy but was deeply skeptical of New Deal domestic legislation and vigorously denounced the administration's attempt to reorganize the Supreme Court. Stimson kept a watchful eye on the developing drama in foreign affairs. He wrote letters to the New York Times demanding action against Mussolini's invasion of Ethiopia, deploring the Ludlow amendment, and favoring an embargo on arms to Spain and Japan. Stimson made himself a champion of China's cause and favored a "get tough" policy toward the Japanese. When the American Committee for Non-Participation in Japanese Aggression was formed in the summer of 1938 Stimson agreed to serve as its honorary chairman.
Stimson had continued to visit Roosevelt at the White House through October, 1934. Then, a misunderstanding occurred and though they corresponded occasionally Stimson's direct access to the president was gone. Stimson was greatly surprised, therefore, when Roosevelt offered him the post of Secretary of War in June, 1940. Stimson accepted, seeing the invitation as a call to duty. Stimson's frequent outspoken remarks about the need for United States aid to help Europe fight fascism had no doubt impressed the president. But, the appointment was also a political stroke. Roosevelt on the eve of his campaign for a third term had hoped to confound his critics by creating a "cabinet of national unity." When the announcement was made at the Republican National Convention then meeting in Philadelphia, Stimson and the new Secretary of the Navy Frank Knox, another Republican, were both read out of the party. His nomination confirmed by the Senate, Stimson was sworn in on July 10.
At first Stimson had doubts as to the permanence of his position in the Roosevelt cabinet. He thought he might be cast out after the November election. At most he foresaw eighteen months preparing the War Department to cope with its increasing responsibilities. One of Stimson's first urgent tasks was the enlarging of the Army. From two hundred thousand in1940 it eventually reached a peak of eight million. Stimson supported enactment of selective service legislation. When the lottery was begun Stimson was the blindfolded man who drew the first capsule. Stimson also advocated support for Britain and worked for the passage of Lend-Lease. The Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor in December, 1941, came almost as a relief to Stimson. The uneasy wait between peace and war was over. Mobilization began in earnest and Stimson took part in strategy sessions between the United States and Britain. He always believed that the European front should take precedence over the Pacific theater and he urged an early cross channel invasion of Europe instead of campaigns in the Mediterranean and Middle East.
During the progress of the war Stimson had to fight continual battles over mobilization of industry and the procurement of supplies and manpower, deal with questions affecting black troops, justify the relocation of West Coast Japanese-American citizens, and develop plans for the postwar government of Germany. He made several inspection tours of army bases in the United States, visited Britain in I943, and joined Omar Bradley and George Patton in France after the invasion of Normandy. His devotion to his work won him the deep friendship of General George Marshal.
The work was rigorous for a man Stimson's age and he continued to amaze the nation with his stamina. His regime called for him to rise at 6:30 for work at the department. After a full day's work he would return to Woodley for a vigorous game of deck tennis. He continued also to enjoy the pleasures of horseback riding. Social engagements were cut to a minimum; he and Mrs. Stimson would spend quiet evenings at home. Almost every weekend they would escape to Highhold to confront the more enjoyable problems of running that household and farm.
As the war in Europe was coming to a conclusion in the spring of 1945 Stimson was beginning to suffer from coronary heart disease. But when President Roosevelt died suddenly in April and an inexperienced Harry Truman came into office Stimson promised Truman that he would remain on the job until the end of war with Japan was in sight.
In the fall of 1941 Stimson had been named by Roosevelt to a committee along with Vannevar Bush and James B. Conant to advise him on nuclear fission policy. When Truman became president, it was Stimson, as senior advisor on the military employment of atomic energy, who first informed him of the existence of the Manhattan project. News of the successful detonation of an atomic bomb was relayed to Stimson at Potsdam on July 16, 1945, where plans for postwar Europe were being discussed. Stimson conveyed the information to Truman and a decision, since the subject of much debate, was made to use the bomb if Japan refused surrender terms. Stimson selected the targets of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
Stimson's last cabinet debate was on the future uses of atomic energy. He insisted that the United States and the Soviets be brought into equal partnership on this subject in an effort to confine the use of atomic energy to peaceful purposes. He felt that for the United States to negotiate with the Soviets with the bomb "on our hip" would "irretrievably embitter," future relations with Russia. He was voicing once again his faith that the best way to make a person or nation trustworthy was to trust them.
The war officially ended on September 2, and Stimson, then 78, weakened by his heart condition, retired from the War Department three weeks later. The years following retirement were not active ones. Stimson returned to Highhold to recuperate, but was plagued by painful attacks of arthritis. Much of his tune was occupied in writing. He wrote articles defending the decision to drop the bomb, justifying the legality of the Nuremburg war crimes trials, and supporting the Marshall plan. In 1948 be completed his autobiography, written with McGeorge Bundy, On Active Service in Peace and War. His last letter to the New York Times was written on March 27, 1950, and decried the attacks by Senator Joseph McCarthy on the State Department. Six months later he died at Highhold.
1. Henry Lewis Stimson and McGeorge Bundy. On Active Service in Peace and War (New York, 1947, 1948), xii. 2. On Active Service, xiii. 3.On Active Service, xv-xvi.
International Treaty for the Limitation and Reduction of Naval Armament (1930 April 22); Armed Forces; Atomic bomb; Law; Tacna-Arica question; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Asia; Latin America; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Nicaragua -- Foreign relations -- United States; Philippines -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1929-1933; United States -- Foreign relations -- Nicaragua; United States -- Foreign relations -- Philippines; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953; Diaries; Lawyers; Public officers; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Astor, William Waldorf Astor, Viscount, 1848-1919; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941; Brüning, Heinrich, 1885-1970; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Bullitt, Wm. Marshall (William Marshall), 1873-1957; Bundy, McGeorge, 1919-1996; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Canfield, Cass, 1897-1986; Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Clark, Grenville, 1882-1967; Coit, John; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Croly, Herbert David, 1869-1930; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Feis, Herbert, 1893-1972; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Ford, Henry Jones, 1851-1925; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-1950; Garrison, Lloyd McKim, 1867-1900; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Hilles, Charles Dewey, 1867-1949; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hornbeck, Stanley Kuhl, 1883-1966; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955; Jay, Pierre, 1870-1949; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Lamont, Thomas W. (Thomas William), 1870-1948; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924; Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, Marquis of, 1882-1940; Lovett, Robert A. (Robert Abercrombie), 1895-1986; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959; Mayo, Katherine, 1868?-1940; McCarthy, Charles, 1873-1921; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Moskowitz, Henry, 1880-; Nagel, Charles, 1849-1940; Newlands, Francis G. (Francis Griffith), 1848-1917; Osmeña, Sergio, 1878-1961; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945; Pepper, George Wharton, 1867-1961; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Rogers, James Grafton, 1883-1971; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Salter, Arthur, 1881-1975; Sanvictores, José; Sherman, P. Tecumseh (Philemon Tecumseh), 1867-1941; Stearns, Alfred E. (Alfred Ernest), 1871-1949; Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946; Stimson, Candace Catherine, 1869-1944; Stimson, Henry Albert, 1842-; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Stimson, Lewis Atterbury, 1844-1917; Stimson, Mabel White, 1866-1955; Stimson, Mary Atterbury; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Thacher, Thomas D. (Thomas Day), 1881-1950; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949; Weston, Catherine Stimson; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927; Woolley, Mary Emma, 1863-1947; United States. Department of State; United States. War Department; Phillips Academy; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1884-1955; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series I-IX and Series XIV are available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 51 instead of Series XIV and FILM HM 52 instead of Series I-IX.
  - Personal Letterpress Volumes
    - 1891 August 25-1900 August 25 (Box 1)
    - 1900 August 27-1907 May 27 (Box 2)
    - 1907 May 25-1910 September 19 (Box 3)
    - 1910 October 17-1913 June 13 (Box 4)
    - 1911 May 22-1913 January 28 (Box 5)
    - 1913 January 20-1913 March 8 (Box 6)
  - Official Letterpress Volumes
    - 1906 February 15-1909 March 30 (Box 6)
    - 1911 May 22-1912 November 12 (Box 7)
    - 1912 Noy 12-1913 March 5 (Box 8)
  - Memoranda and Orders
    - 1911 May 22-1912 March 5 (Box 8)
  - General Correspondence (Box 9)
    - 1884 March 6-1900 January 31 (Box 10)
    - 1900 February 1-1901 October 29 (Box 11)
    - 1901 November 1-1903 November 30 (Box 12)
    - 1903 December 7-1905 May 31 (Box 13)
    - 1905 June 1-1906 February 28 (Box 14)
    - 1906 March 2-1907 January 31 (Box 15)
    - 1907 February-1908 January 14 (Box 16)
    - 1908 January 15-November 30 (Box 17)
    - 1908 December 1-1909 June 18 (Box 18)
    - 1910 nd-1910 April 21 (Box 19)
    - 1910 April 22-September 29 (I-S) (Box 20)
    - 1910 September 29(T-Y)-October 17 (Box 21)
    - 1910 October 18-October 28 (Box 22)
    - 1910 October 29-November 19 (Box 23)
    - 1910 November 21-1911 February 12 (Box 24)
    - 1911 Feb 13-1911 May 13 (C-E), 1911 February 13-May 13 (Box 25)
    - 1911 May 13 (F-H)-1911 Jun 1, 1911 May 13-June 1 (Box 26)
    - 1911 June 2-Ju1 25 (Box 27)
    - 1911 July 26-September 12 (Box 28)
    - 1911 September 13-November 9 (Box 29)
    - 1911 November 10-December 15 (Box 30)
    - 1911 December 16-1912 January 23 (Box 31)
    - 1912 January 25-February 25 (Box 32)
    - 1912 March-April 15 (Box 33)
    - 1912 April 16-June 7 (Box 34)
    - 1912 June 8-August 21 (Box 35)
    - 1912 August 22-October 31 (Box 36)
    - 1912 November-1913 January 1 (Box 37)
    - 1913 January 2-February 22 (Box 38)
    - 1913 February 21-April 30 (Box 39)
    - 1913 May-July 8 (Box 40)
    - 1913 July 9-November 10 (Box 41)
    - 1913 November 11-1914 January 16 (Box 42)
    - 1914 January 17-March 31 (Box 43)
    - 1914 April-July 15 (Box 44)
    - 1914 July 16-September 16 (Box 45)
    - 1914 September 17-December 16 (Box 46)
    - 1914 December 17-1915 February 9 (Box 47)
    - 1915 February 10-April 26 (Box 48)
    - 1915 April 27-June 3 (Box 49)
    - 1915 June 4-July 7 (Box 50)
    - 1915 July 8-August 31 (Box 51)
    - 1915 September-October 19 (Box 52)
    - 1915 October 20-December 21 (Box 53)
    - 1915 December 22-1916 February 14 (Box 54)
    - 1916 February 15-March 24 (Box 55)
    - 1916 March 25-May 20 (Box 56)
    - 1916 March 21-August 17 (Box 57)
    - 1916 August 18-November 3 (Box 58)
    - 1916 November 4-1917 January 12 (Box 59)
    - 1917 January 13-February 21 (Box 60)
    - 1917 February 22-April 3 (Box 61)
    - 1917 April 4-May 21 (Box 62)
    - 1917 May 22-August 31 (Box 63)
    - 1917 September 1-1918 February 13 (Box 64)
    - 1918 February 14-August 14 (Box 65)
    - 1918 August 16-1919 February 28 (Box 66)
    - 1919 March-May 20 (Box 67)
    - 1919 May 21-September 9 (Box 68)
    - 1919 September 10-November 19 (Box 69)
    - 1919 November 20-1920 January 20 (Box 70)
    - 1920 January 20-March 20 (Box 71)
    - 1920 March 21-June 30 (Box 72)
    - 1920 June-September 27 (Box 73)
    - 1920 September 28-December 31 (Box 74)
    - 1921 nd-1921 March 31 (Box 75)
    - 1921 April-August 26 (Box 76)
    - 1921 August 27-December 30 (Box 77)
    - 1922 nd-1922 April 29 (Box 78)
    - 1922 May-September 30 (Box 79)
    - 1922 October-1923 January 26 (Box 80)
    - 1923 January 27-June 4 (Box 81)
    - 1923 July 5-December 7 (Box 82)
    - 1923 December 8-1924 March 25 (Box 83)
    - 1924 March 26-September 30 (Box 84)
    - 1924 October-December 18 (Box 85)
    - 1924 December 19-1925 March 10 (Box 86)
    - 1925 March 11-June 10 (Box 87)
    - 1925 June 11-October 20 (Box 88)
    - 1925 October 21-1926 January 11 (Box 89)
    - 1926 January 12-April 9 (Box 90)
    - 1926 April 10-June 25 (Box 91)
    - 1926 June 26-December 9 (Box 92)
    - 1926 December 10-1927 March 31 (Box 93)
    - 1927 April-June 30 (Box 94)
    - 1927 July-October 18 (Box 95)
    - 1927 October 19-December 6 (Box 96)
    - 1927 December 7-December 23 (Box 97)
    - 1927 December 24-1928 January 31 (Box 98)
    - 1928 February-April 18 (Box 99)
    - 1928 April 19-July 15 (Box 100)
    - 1928 July 16-November 21 (Box 101)
    - 1928 November 22-1929 February 18 (Box 102)
    - 1929 February 19-April 30 (Box 103)
    - 1929 May 1-September 19 (Box 104)
    - 1929 September 21-1930 March 10 (Box 105)
    - 1930 March 11-July 21 (Box 106)
    - 1930 July 22-February 25 (Box 107)
    - 1931 February 26-June 30 (Box 108)
    - 1931 Jul-1932 Jan 26, 1931 July 22-1931 February 25 (Box 109)
    - 1932 January 27-June 2 (Box 110)
    - 1932 June 4-October 31 (Box 111)
    - 1932 November-1933 February 16 (Box 112)
    - 1933 February 18-May 3 (Box 113)
    - 1933 May 5-October 20 (Box 114)
    - 1933 October 23-1934 February 2 (Box 115)
    - 1934 February 3-May 10 (Box 116)
    - 1934 May 11-September 29 (Box 117)
    - 1934 October 1-1935 February 6 (Box 118)
    - 1935 February 7-July 20 (Box 119)
    - 1935 July 21-November 30 (Box 120)
    - 1935 December-1936 May 23 (Box 121)
    - 1936 May 25-November 13 (Box 122)
    - 1936 Noy 16-1937 March 29 (Box 123)
    - 1937 March 30-September 13 (Box 124)
    - 1937 September 14-November 30 (Box 125)
    - 1937 December-1938 February 22 (Box 126)
    - 1938 February 23-May 3 (Box 127)
    - 1938 June 1-November 18 (Box 128)
    - 1938 November 20-1939 March 8 (Box 129)
    - 1939 March 9-May 6 (Box 130)
    - 1939 May 8-September 30 (Box 131)
    - 1939 October-1940 January 11 (Box 132)
    - 1940 June 12-April 30 (Box 133)
    - 1940 May-June 22 (Box 134)
    - 1940 June 23-October 23 (Box 135)
    - 1940 October 24-1941 March 10 (Box 136)
    - 1941 March 11-July 25 (Box 137)
    - 1941 July 26-December 17 (Box 138)
    - 1941 December 18-1942 April 30 (Box 139)
    - 1942 May-October 16 (Box 140)
    - 1942 October 17-1943 April 12 (Box 141)
    - 1943 April 13-September 30 (Box 142)
    - 1943 October 1-1944 January 31 (Box 143)
    - 1944 February-1944 April 19 (Box 144)
    - 1944 April 21-July 31 (Box 145)
    - 1944 August-November 20 (Box 146)
    - 1944 November 21-1945 February 16 (Box 147)
    - 1945 February 18-May 31 (Box 148)
    - 1945 June-September 15 (Box 149)
    - 1945 September 16-October 10 (Box 150)
    - 1945 October 11-December 18 (Box 151)
    - 1945 December 19-1946 May 14 (Box 152)
    - 1946 May 15-November 14 (Box 153)
    - 1946 November 15-1947 February 14 (Box 154)
    - 1947 February 15-June 20 (Box 155)
    - 1947 June 21-October 31 (Box 156)
    - 1947 November 1-1948 February 12 (Box 157)
    - 1948 February 13-May 10 (Box 158)
    - 1948 May 11-September 30 (Box 159)
    - 1948 October 1-1949 March 14 (Box 160)
    - 1949 March 15-September 21 (Box 161)
    - 1949 September 22-1950 February 28 (Box 162)
    - 1950 March-July 19 (Box 163)
    - 1950 July 20-September 30 (Box 164)
    - 1950 October 1-October 20, undated (Box 165)
  - Correspondence Mabel W. Stimson, 1891-1955 (Box 166)
  - Letters of Condolence
    - 1950 Oct 20--1950 Oct 31 (Box 167)
    - 1950 Nov 1--1952 Jan (Box 168)
  - Additional Enclosures (Box 169)
- Memoranda, Minutes of Meetings, Series II
  - Feb 25-Sep 24, 1929 (Box 170, Folder 1)
  - H. L. S. memorandum of trip to Apidan, Oct. 5-7 with memoranda marked A-D attached, 1929 October 7 (Box 170, Folder 2)
  - H. L. S. memorandum of papers drawn up during Prime Minister MacDonald' s visit with memoranda I, la, II, IIa, lIb, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, IX, X, and misc. papers marked "X" attached, 1929 October 9 (Box 170, Folder 3)
  - 1929 Dec (Box 170, Folder 4)
  - memoranda re: The world court, 1929 December or 1930 (Box 170, Folder 5)
  - 1930 January (Box 170, Folder 6)
  - 1931 Jan (Box 170, Folder 7)
  - 1931 Jun, no date -1931 Jun 13 (Box 170, Folder 8)
  - Jun 14-Jul 6, 1931 (Box 170, Folder 9)
  - 1931 Jul-Aug (Box 170, Folder 10)
  - 1931 Oct (Box 170, Folder 11)
  - 1931 Nov (Box 170, Folder 12)
  - 1931 Dec (Box 170, Folder 13)
  - 1932 Jan, no date - Jan 21, 1932 (Box 170, Folder 14)
  - 1932 Feb-May (Box 170, Folder 15)
  - 1932 Sep 11 (Box 170, Folder 16)
  - 1932 Nov (Box 170, Folder 17)
  - 1932, no date (Box 170, Folder 18)
  - 1932 Dec (Box 170, Folder 19)
  - 1933 Jan-Feb (Box 170, Folder 20)
  - 1933 Mar-Nov (Box 170, Folder 21)
  - Jul 12-Sep 27, 1940 (Box 171, Folder 1)
  - Oct 1-31, 1940 (Box 171, Folder 2)
  - Nov 1-29, 1940 (Box 171, Folder 3)
  - 1940 Dec, no date-Dec 2-16, 1940 (Box 171, Folder 4)
  - 1941 Jan, no date, Jan 9-23, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 5)
  - Feb 13-Mar 28, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 6)
  - Apr 4-Apr 25, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 7)
  - May-May 23 1941 (Box 171, Folder 8)
  - Jun 5-Jul 21, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 9)
  - 1941 Aug, no date-Sep 25, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 10)
  - Oct 4-Dec 26, 1941 (Box 171, Folder 11)
  - Jan 4-30, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 12)
  - Feb 6--27, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 13)
  - Mar 10-Apr 24, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 14)
  - 1942 May, no date, May 1-[Jul 23, 1942] (Box 171, Folder 15)
  - Sep 1-29, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 16)
  - Oct 2-29, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 17)
  - [Nov 6, 1942] -Nov 20, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 18)
  - Dec 4-31, 1942 (Box 171, Folder 19)
  - 1943 Jan, no date, Jan 8-Feb 19, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 20)
  - Mar 4-Apr 30, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 21)
  - May 2-26, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 22)
  - Jun 1-18, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 23)
  - Jun 21-29, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 24)
  - [Jul 1, 1943]-Jul 30, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 25)
  - Observations and report on overseas trip, 1943 July 8-31 (Box 171, Folder 26)
  - Aug 10-12, 19143 (Box 171, Folder 27)
  - Sep 2-27, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 28)
  - 1943 Oct, no date, Oct 1-29, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 29)
  - Nov 1-27, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 30)
  - 1943 Dec, no date, Dec 2-30, 1943 (Box 171, Folder 31)
  - Jan 4-Feb 18, 19144 (Box 172, Folder 1)
  - Mar 3-29, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 2)
  - Apr 12, 18, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 3)
  - May 17-31, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 4)
  - Jun 8-30, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 5)
  - 1944 Jul (Box 172, Folder 6)
  - Aug 23-25, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 7)
  - Sep 4-26, 1944 (Box 172, Folder 8)
  - compilation of memoranda re: the treatment of Germany, 1944 September (Box 172, Folder 9)
  - 1944 Oct (Box 172, Folder 10)
  - 1944 Nov (Box 172, Folder 11)
  - 1944 Dec (Box 172, Folder 12)
  - compilations of memos re: the Army Pearl Harbor Board investigation, 1945 (Box 172, Folder 13)
  - 1945 no date, 1945 Jan (Box 172, Folder 14)
  - 1945 Feb-Mar (Box 172, Folder 15)
  - 1945 Apr (Box 172, Folder 16)
  - 1945 May (Box 172, Folder 17)
  - 1945 Jun (Box 172, Folder 18)
    General note
    See: Series III, Box 186, Folder 3a, Cary, Otis, "The Sparing of Kyoto - Mr. Stimson's 'Pet City'", Japan Quarterly, Oct-Dec 1975
  - 1945 Jul (Box 172, Folder 19)
  - 1945 Aug-Sep (Box 172, Folder 20)
  - Proceedings before the Army Pearl Harbor Board (1), 1944 September 26 (Box 173, Folder 1)
  - Index to papers of R. L. S. testimony to Pearl Harbor Board (Box 173, Folder 2)